Guide to the Stanford University, University Services, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, University Services, records
1936-1957
SC0040
Stanford University. University Services.
3 Linear feet
Correspondence, with some reports, minutes, and pamphlets, relating to the activities of the University Services Office. Subjects include the Army Specialized Training Program, California Professional Survey for the War Manpower Commission, Food Research Institute project on food in Germany, tropical disease survey in Guatemala, foreign relief and rehabilitation research, and the development of Stanford scientific research facilities, particularly the Ryan High Voltage Laboratory. The collection also includes other papers relating to Dr. Hanna's work at Stanford and with various national committees; correspondents include Ray Lyman Wilbur and Donald B. Tresidder.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Dr. Paul R. Hanna, 1968.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The University Services office of Stanford University (1942-1954) was established to carry out a program of service on a contractual basis, focusing on the region, the nation, international studies, and business and industry. Paul R. Hanna, professor in the School of Education, was its first director, serving from 1942-1944.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, with some reports, minutes, and pamphlets, relating to the activities of the University Services Office. Subjects include the Army Specialized Training Program, California Professional Survey for the War Manpower Commission, Food Research Institute project on food in Germany, tropical disease survey in Guatemala, foreign relief and rehabilitation research, and the development of Stanford scientific research facilities, particularly the Ryan High Voltage Laboratory. The collection also includes other papers relating to Dr. Hanna's work at Stanford and with various national committees; correspondents include Ray Lyman Wilbur and Donald B. Tresidder.
Access Terms
Hanna, Paul Robert, 1902-1988.; Stanford University. University Services.; Tresidder, Donald Bertrand, 1894-1948; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949; Education, Higher--Research.; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 --Manpower.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - American Council on Education – Latin American Film Project (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Legion Auxiliary Questionnaire (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Army Map Service (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Army Specialized Training Program – Official Correspondence – War Department [1 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Army Specialized Training Program – Official Correspondence – War Department [2 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Army Specialized Training Program – Official Correspondence – War Department [3 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - ASTD (Army Specialized Training Division) - Engineering (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - ASTD - Professional (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ASPO (American Society of Planning Officials) – Committee on Education [1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - ASPO (American Society of Planning Officials) – Committee on Education [2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ASTP (Army Specialized Training Program) – 9L (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ASTP – Advanced Engineers (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ASTP – FALS (Foreign Area and Language Studies) – European (Duplicate) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ASTP – FALS – Far Eastern [1 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ASTP – FALS – Far Eastern [2 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ASTP – FALS – Far Eastern [3 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - ASTP – FALS – Official Correspondence [1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - ASTP – FALS – Official Correspondence [2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - ASTP – FALS – Pre-Professional (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - ASTP – Reserve Program (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ASTP – Basic Engineers (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - BEW (Board of Economic Welfare) – Peru (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bolivian Education (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bureau of Reclamation – Power Lines (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - CATS (Civilian Affairs Training School) – Europe (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Campus Civil Defense – Spring 1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chinese (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Central Valley Project #1 [1 of 4] (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Central Valley Project #1 [2 of 4] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Central Valley Project #1 [3 of 4] (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Central Valley Project #1 [4 of 4] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Central Valley Project #2 [1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Central Valley Project #2 [2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Central Valley Project – Part I, The Significance of the Problem [1 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Central Valley Project – Part I, The Significance of the Problem [2 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Central Valley Project – Part I, The Significance of the Problem [3 of 3] (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Central Valley Project – CHP (California Housing and Planning) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Civil Affairs Specialists Training Program (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Commission on Resources and Education (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Committee on Community Survey of Child Welfare (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Committee on University Services (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Curriculum for Planners (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Deferment from Selective Service (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Electron Optics (Marton) (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - European Area and Language School – ASTP – War Department (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - European Civil Affairs Specialists – PMGO (Provost Marshall General’s Office) – War Department [1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - European Civil Affairs Specialists – PMGO (Provost Marshall General’s Office) – War Department [2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Expenses (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Faculty – Additional Teaching Fields (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Faculty Pool (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Far East Civil Affairs Specialists (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Far Eastern Area and Language Study – ASTP (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Foreign Area and Language Study – ASTP (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Foreign Area and Language and Civil Affairs Specialists – Official Correspondence – War Department [1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Foreign Area and Language and Civil Affairs Specialists – Official Correspondence – War Department [2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Foundations and Gifts - General (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Guatemala – Tropical Disease Report ("Preliminary Report on the Parasitic and Other Infectious Diseases of Guatemala" by Edward P. Mumford and John L. Mohr) (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Guggenheim Foundation (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - High Voltage Laboratory – Stanford University (typescript report, 1943, and articles) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - ICA (International Cooperation Administration) – New Contract [1 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ICA (International Cooperation Administration) – New Contract [2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Institute for Educational Interpretation (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Illumination Laboratory – Stanford University (typescript report with photo 1943 and articles) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Institute on Educational Reconstruction in Central and Eastern Europe – NYU, April 7-8, 1943 [1 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Institute on Educational Reconstruction in Central and Eastern Europe – NYU, April 7-8, 1943 [2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations (Duke) [1 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations (Duke) [2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Inter-American Affairs (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Japanese Language Unit – Signal Corps – ASTD (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - W. K. Kellog Foundation – Post-War Planning – School of Education (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Latin American Training Center (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Maritime Commission (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Materials for August 24, 1942 (A Proposal to Organize the Stanford Resources for Public Service) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence from Stanford (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence from Washington (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - National Manpower Council – New York, February 7-8, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Navy Testing (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Office of Strategic Services #1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Office of Strategic Services #2 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - OMPG (Office of Provost Marshall General) – Civil Affairs Training Specialists (Duplicate) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - OSRD (Office of Scientific Research and Development) – Baumberger Physiology (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - OSS (Office of Strategic Services) – Far Eastern Research (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - OSS – Project #1 – Food in Germany (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Overseas Service – Wallace Committee (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Overseas Service – Government Departments (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - OWI (Office of War Information) – Foreign Rehabilitation (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Personnel Psychology (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Personnel Psychology – 9P-ASTP (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Pool of Possible Personnel – Military Government - ASTP (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Pre-flight Aeronautics Course (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Proposed Advance School – Public Service (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Proposed Inter-American Center (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Proposal for Stanford College (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Proposed Survey of San Francisco Bay Area (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Public Buildings Administration (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Radar School (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Regional Planning (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Rehabilitation – American Red Cross (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Rehabilitation Program #1 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Rehabilitation Program #2 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Report on Germany (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Mrs. Roosevelt – OCD (Office of Civilian Defense) – Proposals by Paul R. Hanna and Floyd W. Reeves re youth and national defense, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - ROTC – ASTD – Quartermaster (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Ryan Laboratory (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - School for Labor Leaders (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Science Mobilization Bill (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - SPARS – correspondence re Stanford's possible role in training the women's reserve of the Coast Guard, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - STATE – Hoover Library (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - State Department – Foreign Relief and Rehabilitation (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Testing Program – ASTD (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Tropical Disease Survey – report and correspondence re Stanford project (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - University Services - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - WACS (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - WACS – Physical Therapy (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - War – Army Institute (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - War Department – Military Government Source Materials [1 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - War Department – Military Government Source Materials [2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - War Production Board – Office of Production Research and Development (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Washington - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Washington – Stanford Correspondence from September 1943 [1 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Washington – Stanford Correspondence from September 1943 [2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - “What other Universities are doing that is similar” (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Who’s Who in Latin America #1 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Who’s Who in Latin America #2 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - WMC (War Manpower Commission) – California Professional and Technical Survey (Box 2, Folder 67)